<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter [
<!ENTITY % all.entities SYSTEM "all-entities.ent">
%all.entities;
]>
<section version="5.0" xml:id="components"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Components</title>

  <section>
    <title>Overview</title>

    <para>There are four main components that make up the NDO
    utilities:</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>NDOMOD Event Broker Module</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>LOG2NDO Utility</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>FILE2SOCK Utility</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>NDO2DB Daemon</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para>Each component is described in more detail on the following
    pages.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>NDOMOD</title>

    <para>The NDO utilities includes a Nagios event broker module (NDOMOD.O)
    that exports data from the Nagios daemon.</para>

    <para>Assuming that Nagios has been compiled with the event broker enabled
    (this is the default), you can configure Nagios to load the NDOMOD module
    during runtime. Once the module has been loaded by the Nagios daemon, it
    can access all of the data and logic present in the running Nagios
    process.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Loaded NDOMOD Event broker Module</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="html">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/fig5.png" format="PNG"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>The NDOMOD module has been designed to export configuration data, as
    well as information about various runtime events that occur in the
    monitoring process, from the Nagios daemon. The module can send this data
    to a standard file, a Unix domain socket, or a TCP socket.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>NDOMOD Capabilities</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="../images/fig6.png"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>The NDOMOD module writes data in a format that the NDO2DB daemon
    (described later) can understand.</para>

    <para>If the NDOMOD module is writing its output to a file, you can
    configure it to periodically rotate and/or process the output file using a
    predefined Nagios command. This can be useful if you want to transfer the
    output file to another physical machine (using SSH, etc. ) and send its
    contents to the NDO2DB daemon using the FILE2SOCK utility (described
    later).</para>

    <para>If the NDOMOD module is writing it output to a TCP or Unix domain
    socket, it has some resistance to connection dropouts. The module will
    attempt to cache its output until it can (re)connect to the socket for
    writing. This is helpful if the process that creates and listens on the
    socket needs to be restarted, etc.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>LOG2NDO</title>

    <para>The LOG2NDO utility has been designed to allow you to import
    historical Nagios and NetSaint log files into a database via the NDO2DB
    daemon (<link linkend="ndo2db-description">described later</link>). The
    utility works by sending historical log file data to a standard file, a
    Unix domain socket, or a TCP socket in a format the NDO2DB daemon
    understands. The NDO2DB daemon can then be used to process that output and
    store the historical logfile information in a database.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>LOG2NDO Utility</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="../images/fig7.png"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>FILE2SOCK</title>

    <para>The FILE2SOCK utility is quite simple. Its reads input from a
    standard file (or STDIN) and writes all of that data to either a Unix
    domain socket or TCP socket. The data that is read is not processed in any
    way before it is sent to the socket.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>FILE2SOCK Utility</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="../images/fig8.png"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>This utility is useful if you are directing the output of the NDOMOD
    event broker module and/or LOG2NDO utility to a standard file. Once these
    components finish writing their output to a file, you can use the
    FILE2SOCK utility to send the contents of the file to the NDO2DB daemon's
    TCP or Unix domain socket.</para>
  </section>

  <section label="NDO2DB" xml:id="ndo2db-description">
    <title>NDO2DB</title>

    <para>The NDO2DB utility is designed to take the data output from the
    NDOMOD and LOG2NDO components and store it in a MySQL or PostgreSQL
    database.</para>

    <para>When it starts, the NDO2DB daemon creates either a TCP or Unix
    domain socket and waits for clients to connect. NDO2DB can run either as a
    standalone, multi-process daemon or under INETD (if using a TCP
    socket).</para>

    <figure>
      <title>NDO2DB Daemon</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="../images/fig9.png"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>Multiple clients can connect to the NDO2DB daemon's socket and
    transmit data simultaneously. A seperate NDO2DB process is spawned to
    handle each new client that connects. Data is read from each client and
    stored in a user-specified database for later retrieval and
    processing.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>NDO2DB with multiple Clients</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="../images/fig10.png"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>The NDO2DB daemon currently supports only MySQL databases, but
    future support for PostgreSQL databases is planned.</para>
  </section>
</section>
