<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter [
<!ENTITY % all.entities SYSTEM "all-entities.ent">
%all.entities;
]>
<section version="5.0" xml:id="example-configs"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Example Configurations</title>

  <section>
    <title>Single Server, Single Instance Setup</title>

    <para>The easiest configuration occurs when you have a single Nagios
    instance running on your network. In this case, installing and configuring
    the various components of the NODUTILS addon is fairly
    straighforward.</para>

    <para>The following diagram illustrates how the various components can fit
    together in a single server, single Nagios instance setup....</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Single Server, Single Instance Setup</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="../images/fig11.png"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>Here's a description of what's happening at each point in the
    diagram:</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>The NDOMOD module is configured with an instance name of
        "default" since there is only one instance of Nagios that is running
        on the network.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>While the Nagios daemon is running and performing its usual
        business of monitoring the network, the NDOMOD module is sending
        configuration data and event information to the TCP or Unix domain
        socket that was created by the NDO2DB daemon.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The NDO2DB daemon reads data that is coming into the socket from
        the NDOMOD module.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The NDO2DB daemon processes and transforms data that has been
        received from the NDOMOD module.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The processed data is stored in a database for later retrieval
        and processing.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para>This example assumes that:</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Nagios is configured to load the NDOMOD module at
        startup.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The NDO2DB daemon (which is a seperate process from the Nagios
        daemon) is running.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Single Server, Multiple Instance Setup</title>

    <para>Another simple configuration can be used when you have a multiple
    Nagios instances running on a single server. Installing and configuring
    the various components of the NODUTILS addon is similiar as to what was
    shown in the previous example.</para>

    <para>The following diagram illustrates how the various components can fit
    together in a single server, multiple Nagios instance setup....</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Single Server, Multiple Instance Setup</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="../images/fig12.png"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>You'll notice that the diagram above is similiar to the one for the
    single-server, single instance configuration. The main difference is that
    there are now three (3) different Nagios daemons instead of just
    one.</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Each Nagios daemon loads the NODMOD module at startup with a
        unique instance name. In this example the instances are simply named
        "nagios1", "nagios2" and "nagios3".</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Each NDOMOD module sends configuration data and event
        information for its specific instance of the Nagios daemon to the TCP
        or Unix domain socket that was created by the NDO2DB daemon.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The NDO2DB daemon reads data that is coming into the socket from
        the three NDOMOD modules.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The NDO2DB daemon processes and transforms data that has been
        received from the NDOMOD modules.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The processed data is stored in a database for later retrieval
        and processing. Data from each instance of Nagios is kept seperate
        (using the instance names as unique identifiers) in the
        database.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Single Server, Single Instance Log File Import</title>

    <para>There are two reasons you'll probably want to import your Nagios log
    files into the same database that Nagios configuration and event data is
    stored in:</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Historical log file data isn't imported into the database by
        default and having a record of events that occurred before you
        implemented the NDOUTILS addon is probably desireable.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The NDOMOD module is not able to process realtime log entries
        from the time right after the Nagios daemon starts to the time that
        the NDOMOD module is loaded by the Nagios daemon. This "blackout
        period" is unavoidable and causing log entries such as "Nagios 2.0
        starting..." to be missed by the NDOMOD module. Thus, importing
        day-old Nagios log files on a daily basis (via a cron job) is
        recommended.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <figure>
      <title>Single Server, Single Instance Log File Import</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="../images/fig13.png"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>Here's a description of what's happening at each point in the
    diagram:</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Historical Nagios log files are read by the LOG2NDO
        utility.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The LOG2NDO utility processes the contents of the log files and
        tags them with an instance name of "default". This instance name must
        match the same instance name used by the NDOMOD module in the Nagios
        daemon.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Historical log file data is sent to the TCP or Unix domain
        socket in a format that the NDO2DB daemon can understand.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The NDO2DB daemon reads the log file data from the Unix domain
        socket.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The NDO2DB daemon processes the log file data.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Historical log file data is stored in a database for later
        retrieval and processing. The NDO2DB daemon will perform some checks
        to make sure it doesn't re-import duplicate historical log entries, so
        running the LOG2NDO utility on the same historical log file multiple
        times shouldn't have any negative side effects.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para>That's it! Pretty simple.</para>
  </section>
</section>
