<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter [
<!ENTITY % all.entities SYSTEM "all-entities.ent">
%all.entities;
]>
<section version="5.0" xml:id="intro" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Introduction</title>

  <section>
    <title>Purpose</title>

    <para>The NDOUTILS addon is designed to store all configuration and event
    data from Nagios in a database. Storing information from Nagios in a
    database will allow for quicker retrieval and processing of that data and
    will help serve as a foundation for the development of a new PHP-based web
    interface in future Nagios versions.</para>

    <para>MySQL databases are currently supported by the addon. Other
    databases will be supported in the next versions.</para>

    <para>The development for this will start right after the next stable
    NDOUtils release (1.6).</para>

    <para>Support for other database servers may be added if there is
    sufficient user interest and even more user who are interested in
    testing.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Design Overview</title>

    <para>The NDOUTILS addon was designed to work for users who have:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Single Nagios installations</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Multiple standalone or "vanilla" Nagios installations</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Multiple Nagios installations in distributed, redundant, and/or
        fail over environments</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Data from each Nagios process (hereafter referred to as "instances")
    can be stored either in the same database or different databases than data
    from other Nagios instances.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Possible Designs</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="../images/fig1.png"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>Although not yet supported, future development should allow for data
    from any given Nagios instance to be stored in multiple databases if
    desired.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Future development: One Instance, multiple databases</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="../images/fig2.png"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Instances</title>

    <para>Each Nagios process, whether it is a standalone monitoring server,
    or part of a distributed, redundant, or fail over monitoring setup, is
    referred to as an "instance". In order to maintain the integrity of stored
    data, each Nagios instance must be labeled with a unique identifier or
    name.</para>

    <para>You can choose the name of each Nagios instance to suit your needs.
    For instance, you could choose to name Nagios instances based on their
    geographical location...</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Instance names based on geographical locations</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="../images/fig3.png"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>Or you could name Nagios instances based on their purpose...</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Instance names based on their purpose</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="../images/fig4.png"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>How you name Nagios instances is up to you. The key point to
    remember is that each and every Nagios process must have its own unique
    instance name.</para>

    <para>More information on how instance names come into play will be
    discussed in sections 3 and 4.</para>
  </section>
</section>
